Evelyn Hawes Papers 1888-1975
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Evelyn Hawes Papers
1888-1975
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 226
Evelyn Hawes
28 containers 14 linear feet
This collection consists primarily of literary manuscripts, galley proofs, printed materials, and correspondence related to Evelyn Hawes' writing projects, including her books Proud Vision (1964), The Happy Land (1965), A Madras-Type Jacket (1967), and Six Nights a Week (1971).
Author Evelyn Johnson Hawes was born in Colville, Washington to W. Lon Johnson and Iva (Dickey) Johnson. She attended Washington State University and the University of Washington, receiving her bachelor's degree from UW in 1936.
Hawes taught writing as member of the faculty at several institutions, including the University of Washington, the University of Cincinnati, Canisius College, Amherst Central Adult School, and the State University of New York at Buffalo.
Hawes' published works include many articles and stories, and several books: They Also Serve (1943), Proud Vision; the History of the Buffalo General Hospital: The First Hundred Years (1964), The Happy Land (1965), Boys Are All Right, Butà (1965), A Madras-type Jacket (1967), and Six Nights a Week (1971).
This collection consists primarily of literary manuscripts, galley proofs, printed materials, and correspondence related to Evelyn Hawes' writing projects. Other materials include correspondence and other documentation related to Hawes' participation in the National League of American Pen Women, along with some personal and family items, and some correspondence related to her teaching.
When processing of this collection was completed in 2005, the existing order was generally maintained. Because the papers were received in separate accessions, there are some overlapping sequences in the "Correspondence" series. The "Miscellaneous Correspondence" and "Miscellaneous" subseries were created during processing to facilitate access to unsorted or unidentified materials.
This collection is open for research use.
Evelyn Hawes donated this collection of her literary papers to the Washington State University Libraries in 1969 and 1970.
Related materials may be found in Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections:
Cage 195, Lon Johnson Papers, 1912-1967
Unprocessed manuscript collections:
MS 1987-41, Evelyn Hawes and Lon Johnson Papers
MS 1982-62, Evelyn Hawes Papers
MS 1994-55, Evelyn Hawes Papers
Hawes, Evelyn.; National League of American Pen Women.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Literature
- Correspondence, 1921-1975, undated; 1
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1948-1972, undated; 1.1
    - Taylor Caldwell, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Foreign exchange students, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Peggy Griffenhagen, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nat Hawes, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sloan Wilson, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - 1948-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1975; 1.2
    - Amherst Central Senior High School, Adult Education, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Canisius College, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chi Omega, 1950-1967 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    - Ann Elmo Agency
      - 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
    - Charles Ferguson, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Harcourt, Brace and World, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
    - Hawes Christmas letters, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - W. Lon Johnson, 1948-1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Betty Lowman, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Ripley's, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - W.S. Wabnitz and Rachel Wabnitz
      - 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
      - 1961-1966 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Personal
      - 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 37-42)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 45-46)
    - Johnson family, 1921-1940 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Childhood and undated, ca. 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Book promotion
      - Tacoma, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Cincinnati, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      - Travel, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Magazine correspondence
      - Aero-Mayflower (article on moving), 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 52)
      - American, Seventeen, Holland's, Parents, etc., 1950-1957 (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Colliers, Companion, McCall's, Thomas Y. Crowell Co., 1950-1964 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Ann Elmo (agent), 1952-1959 (Box 5, Folder 55-57)
      - Charles Ferguson (editor, The Reader's Digest), Robert Lescher, 1958-1965 (Box 6, Folder 58-60)
    - Ladies' Home Journal (and various book publishers)
      - 1950-1958 (Box 6, Folder 61-62)
      - 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 63)
      - Parents Magazine, Eldorado, Reader's Digest, The Writer, etc, 1957-1964 (Box 6, Folder 64)
      - Redbook, Good Housekeeping, Cosmopolitan, Harper's Bazaar (primarily printed rejection notices), undated (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Saturday Evening Post
      - 1950-1955 (Box 6, Folder 66-67)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Miscellaneous small magazines, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Publishers, 1949-1954 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1955 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Fan letters
      - Fan letters, replies to publicity, letters regarding The Happy Land, 1965-1969 (Box 7, Folder 72-76)
      - Fan letters, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 77-80)
      - Personal and fan letters, 1962-1975 (Box 8, Folder 81-85)
    - General, 1964-1969
      - 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 86)
      - 1967 (Box 9, Folder 87-88)
      - 1968 (Box 9, Folder 89-90)
      - 1969 (Box 9, Folder 91)
      - General, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 92-95)
  - Subject files, 1944-1972; 1.3
    - Amherst Eight O'clock Club, undated (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - High school fraternities and sororities, 1950-1957 (Box 9, Folder 97-98)
    - National League of American Pen Women
      - Awards chairman, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 99)
      - Banquet, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 100)
      - Book review and correspondence, Marion Benasutti, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 101)
      - Contest rules, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 102)
      - Contest winners, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 103-104)
      - Fiction contest: Pompea, Mudra, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 105)
      - General correspondence, 1954-1966 (Box 10, Folder 106)
      - Invitations and inquiry letters, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 107)
      - Non-fiction: Alice Partridge, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 108)
      - Juveniles: LeVee, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 109)
      - Letters, biennial, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 110)
      - Letters contest, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 111)
      - Letters prize awards, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 112)
      - Willa Low, Convention Salt Lake, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 113)
      - Elizabeth Rider Montgomery reports, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 114)
      - Poetry, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 115)
      - President, Letters banquet, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 116-117)
      - Publications, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 118)
      - Report (addenda), Pen Women Award Funds, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 119)
      - Roster chairman, The Pen Woman, Lee Waldrop, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 120)
      - "Sometimes I Write" (article), 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 121)
      - Western New York Branch achievements, 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 122-124)
      - Winners (outgoing letters), 7 February, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 125)
      - Workshops, Sarah Brock, 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 126)
      - Miscellaneous, 1964-1968 (Box 12, Folder 127)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s (Box 12, Folder 128)
      - Plywood, 1944 (Box 12, Folder 129)
- Miscellaneous and unidentified materials, 1888-1968; 2
  - Miscellaneous, 1945-1968, undated (Box 13, Folder 130)
  - News clippings
    - circa 1930s-1950s (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - 1964-1967 (Box 13, Folder 132-134)
  - Radio interview, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Reviews (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Memorabilia
    - Junior high school pictures and activities, circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Family diplomas and miscellaneous items, 1888-1935 (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Miscellaneous, 1932-1935 (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Programs and cards, 1908-1935 (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Scrapbook (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Skookum (yearbook of Colville High School), 1929, 1931 (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - Photographs (Box 14, Folder 143-144)
- Manuscripts and book files, 1929-1971, undated; 3
  - Miscellaneous or unlabeled manuscripts, 1929-1930, undated; 3.1
    - Journal, 1929-1930 (Box 14, Folder 145-147)
    - Judy Brown article, handwritten copy, undated (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - Young Marrieds in Australia, undated (Box 14, Folder 149)
    - Miscellaneous or unidentified manuscripts, undated (Box 14, Folder 150)
    - Rough drafts, undated (Box 14, Folder 151-154)
  - Manuscripts and galley proofs (books and articles), printed material, 1936-1971, undated; 3.2
    - A Madras-Type Jacket
      - Manuscript and galley proof as returned from Harcourt, Brace, and World, 1966-1968 (Box 15, Folder 155-158)
      - Manuscript, Harcourt-Brace, Don's corrections, undated (Box 15, Folder 159-161)
      - First draft, 1966, undated (Box 15, Folder 162-164)
      - Redbook, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 165-167)
      - Typewritten corrections, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 168)
      - Second draft, page proofs, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 169-172)
      - "I Loved the Way You Described Aunt Mary" (drafts, correspondence, printed version), 1967-1969 (Box 16, Folder 173)
    - The Happy Land
      - Page proofs, undated (Box 16, Folder 174)
      - Extra pages, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 175)
      - Where Is Eldorado? (earlier title), original of revision, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 176-179)
      - Play, undated (Box 17, Folder 180-182)
      - Final manuscript, undated (Box 17, Folder 183-185)
      - Long version, before cut, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 186-189)
      - Galley proofs, undated (Box 18, Folder 190)
      - Marked galleys, final typed version, undated (Box 18, Folder 191-192)
      - Uncorrected manuscript, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 193-196)
      - "False starts", undated (Box 19, Folder 197)
      - Where Is Eldorado?, work on revising, undated (Box 19, Folder 198-201)
      - The Happy Land (Where Is Eldorado?), corrected manuscript, June, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 202-205)
      - Corrections (typed), final, July 1964 (Box 19, Folder 206-207)
      - Corrections (typed), final, July 1964 (Box 20, Folder 208)
      - Reviews, publicity, 1965, undated (Box 20, Folder 209)
      - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 210)
      - Unlabeled revisions, undated (Box 20, Folder 211)
      - Eldorado cuttings (back from Harcourt), June 1964 (Box 20, Folder 212-214)
      - Eldorado fragments, 1961 beginnings, 1961, undated (Box 20, Folder 215-216)
    - "What Price Conformity?", undated (Box 20, Folder 217)
    - "Who Am I?", undated (Box 20, Folder 218)
    - "Dream of a Far Land", undated (Box 20, Folder 219)
    - "There Is a Season" (4 versions), 1969, undated (Box 20, Folder 220)
    - "Skeleton at the Feast," miscellaneous, 1968, undated (Box 20, Folder 221)
    - Book reviews, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 21, Folder 222-223)
    - "My Dear Friend--My Son," research notes plus final manuscript, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 224-227)
    - "Apocalypse", February 1964 (Box 21, Folder 228)
    - Proud Vision
      - Galley proof, July 1964 (Box 21, Folder 229)
      - Original manuscript, undated (Box 21, Folder 230-233)
    - "School Daze", 1961 (Box 22, Folder 234)
    - "What Price Conformity?", 1961 (Box 22, Folder 234)
    - "Detroit, Where Are You?", undated (Box 22, Folder 235)
    - "How Can I Explain Seattle?", undated (Box 22, Folder 235)
    - "Dream of a Far Land", undated (Box 22, Folder 235)
    - "There Is a Season", undated (Box 22, Folder 235)
    - "Dream of a Far Land," revision, 1962 (Box 22, Folder 236)
    - "Dream of a Far Land", undated (Box 22, Folder 237)
    - "Who Am I?", undated (Box 22, Folder 238)
    - "Bald Knobbers" (fragment), undated (Box 22, Folder 238)
    - "Who Am I?", undated (Box 22, Folder 239-240)
    - "Detroit, Where Are You?", undated (Box 22, Folder 241)
    - "Apocalypse" revision, March 1964 (Box 22, Folder 242)
    - Short stories (later incorporated into The Happy Land), undated (Box 22, Folder 243)
    - "There Is a Season", 1962, undated (Box 22, Folder 244-245)
    - "The Choice", undated (Box 22, Folder 246)
    - "Never So Again", undated (Box 22, Folder 247)
    - "So You Want to Go to College", undated (Box 22, Folder 247)
    - "On the Move: Home Again", undated (Box 22, Folder 248)
    - "Danger! College Freshmen!", 1959 (Box 22, Folder 249)
    - "The Defense Rests", undated (Box 23, Folder 250)
    - "Too Young to Retire: Jobs for Older Women", undated (Box 23, Folder 251)
    - Proud Vision
      - Original manuscript, undated (Box 23, Folder 252-255)
      - Research notes, related documentation, 1962-1965, undated (Box 23, Folder 256-260)
      - Research notes, manuscript, circa 1962 (Box 23, Folder 261)
      - Research notes, manuscript, circa 1962 (Box 24, Folder 262)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 24, Folder 263-265)
      - Buffalo General Hospital, original copy, undated (Box 24, Folder 266-267)
    - "Just to Love", undated (Box 24, Folder 268)
    - Published stories, undated (Box 24, Folder 269)
    - "The Gray Man" (revised to "The Long Night"), 1951-1952 (Box 24, Folder 270)
    - Holland's, 1950-1952 (Box 24, Folder 271)
    - "Sins of the Fathers", 1954 (Box 25, Folder 272)
    - Short stories, articles, 1949-1961, undated (Box 25, Folder 273-278)
    - Twentieth Century Club of Buffalo
      - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 25, Folder 279)
      - Final manuscript, corrections, 1969 (Box 25, Folder 280-283)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 26, Folder 284-287)
    - "They Also Serve" (radio scripts and play), undated (Box 26, Folder 288-289)
    - "Once a Minute"
      - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 26, Folder 290)
      - Drafts, manuscripts, undated (Box 26, Folder 291-293)
    - Short stories, undated (Box 26, Folder 294)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 26, Folder 295)
    - Six Nights a Week
      - Galley proofs, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 296)
      - Corrected galleys, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 297)
      - Final manuscript, correction notes, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 298-300)
      - Fan letters, 1971-1973 (Box 27, Folder 301-303)
    - "I Promise Thee", undated (Box 28, Folder 304)
    - Magazines containing published material
      - 1936-1950 (Box 28, Folder 305)
      - 1952-1959 (Box 28, Folder 306)
      - 1961-1967 (Box 28, Folder 307)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 28, Folder 308)
- Administrative files, 1965-1972; 4
  - Correspondence (primarily between Hawes and Earle Connette), 1965-1972 (Box 28, Folder 309-313)
  - Biographical information, ca. 1970s (Box 28, Folder 314)
  - Processing file (Box 28, Folder 315)
    Iincludes Hawes' listings of materials shipped to WSU, and processing notes regarding preliminary arrangement.